Exercise 1-11. Four main reasons for intonation. Depending on the situation, a
word may be stressed for any of the following reasons. New information,
opinion, contrast, can't. One. New information. It sounds like rain. Rain is
the new information. It's the most important word in that sentence, and you
could replace everything else with da-da-da. Da-da-da, rain will still let you get
your point across. Repeat, da-da-da, rain. It sounds like rain. Make rain very
musical and put it on two notes, rain, da-da-da, rain. It sounds like rain. Two,
opinion. It sounds like rain, but I don't think it is. In this case, intonation
makes the meaning the opposite of what the words say. It looks like a diamond, but I
think it's a zircon. It smells like Chanel, but at that price it's a knockoff.
It feels like. It tastes like. These examples all give the impression that you
mean the opposite of what your senses tell you. Practice the intonation difference
between new information and opinion. It sounds like rain. It's rain. It sounds
like rain, but it's not. Three, contrast. He likes rain, but he hates snow. Like and
hate are contrasted and are the stronger words in the sentence. Four, can't. It
can't rain when there are no clouds. Contractions, shouldn't, wouldn't, etc.,
and negatives, no, not, never, are important words since they totally negate
the meaning of a sentence, but they're usually not stressed. Can't is the
exception.